Guide to the A. Kenneth Pye, Chancellor, Records and Papers, 1960-1983 UA.06.51.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
A. Kenneth Pye, Chancellor, records and papers
1960-1983
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pye, A. Kenneth
UA.06.51.0001
63 Linear Feet
August Kenneth Pye (1931-1994) was twice Chancellor of Duke University (1970-1971 and 1976-1982). In addition to the chancellorship, he was Dean of the School of Law (1968-1970), University Counsel (1971-1974), Acting Dean of the School of Law (1973), Dean of the School of Law (1973-1977), Director of the Center for International Studies (1982-1984), and Samuel Fox Mordecai Professor of Law (1982-1987). Collection includes memoranda, correspondence, published materials, reports, printed matter, clippings and other materials generated by the Office of the Chancellor during Pye's two terms as Chancellor (1970-1971 and 1976-1982). There are also correspondence, speeches, printed matter, and subject files collected by Pye from 1968 to 1976 as Dean of the School of Law, Chancellor, and University Counsel.
42,100 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
The A. Kenneth Pye, Chancellor, Records and Papers were received by the University Archives as transfers between 1977-1995.
Biographical and Historical Note
August Kenneth Pye (1931-1994) was twice Chancellor of Duke University (1970-1971 and 1976-1982). Educated at the University of Buffalo (B.A., 1951) and Georgetown University (J.D., 1953, LL.M., 1955), Pye held the positions of professor and associate dean at the Georgetown University Law Center, 1955-1966. Pye held a number of positions at Duke. In addition to the chancellorship, he was Dean of the School of Law (1968-1970), University Counsel (1971-1974), Acting Dean of the School of Law (1973), Dean of the School of Law (1973-1977), Director of the Center for International Studies (1982-1984), and Samuel Fox Mordecai Professor of Law (1982-1987). Upon leaving Duke University, Pye held the positions of President and Professor of Law at Southern Methodist University, Dallas, Texas (1987-1994).
President Emeritus R.L. Flowers was named Chancellor in 1949. The position was seemingly an honorary one, and there are no records of his tenure. The office was re-established in March 1969, when President Douglas M. Knight wanted an officer to assist with an increasing executive workload. The Chancellor was given responsibility for the internal operation of the University. Under the University By-Laws of May 10, 1988, the Chancellor was an executive officer with powers and duties assigned by the President. The occupants of the office have been Robert L. Flowers (1949-1951), Barnes Woodhall (1969-1970) (pro tem), A. Kenneth Pye (1970-1971), John O. Blackburn (1971-1976), A. Kenneth Pye (1976-1982), and H. Keith H. Brodie (1982-1985). With Dr. Brodie's inauguration as President, the office was left vacant until William G. Anlyan, M.D., was named Chancellor in 1988. He retired in 1990 and was not replaced.
Collection Overview
Collection includes memoranda, correspondence, published materials, reports, printed matter, clippings and other materials generated by the Office of the Chancellor during Pye's two terms as Chancellor (1970-1971 and 1976-1982). There are also correspondence, speeches, printed matter, and subject files collected by Pye from 1968 to 1976 as Dean of the School of Law, Chancellor, and University Counsel.
The first series consists of subject files created during Pye's first tenure as Chancellor, 1970-1971. Subjects include the merger of the Woman's College with Trinity College, an evaluation of the university's relationship with the Army Research Office in Durham, Duke's position on admission standards for student-athletes in the Atlantic Coast Conference, the Summer Transitional Program, international studies, the evaluation of the Navy and Air Force ROTC programs, African-American studies, the Pickets and Protest Policy and student unrest, and regulations pertaining to drug use and other aspects of student life. Administrative officers who communicated with Pye in regard to these matters include James Price, Dean of Undergraduate Education, William Griffith, Dean of Student Affairs, and President Terry Sanford.
The second series consists of subject files created during Pye's second tenure as Chancellor, 1976-1982. As Chancellor, Pye had overall responsibility for planning and budgeting at the university, and the files reflect the retrenchment and long-range planning process that occurred at Duke in the late 1970s and early 1980s. Other subjects include reports on the enrollment of North Carolina students, the admission of African-Americans, A.B. Duke Scholars from the years 1926 to 1981, financial aid and admissions, the Duke University Athletic Association (DUAA), the recruitment and admission of student-athletes, the Commission on Intercollegiate Athletics of the American Council on Education, Title IX of the Education Amendments, affirmative action, planning for the University Center (Bryan University Center), East Campus planning and residential life, the Public Safety department, black affairs, labor relations and unionization, the Nixon Library controversy, the American Dance Festival, the Marine Laboratory, and forestry, nursing, sociology, and education programs.
A subseries of the subject files created during Pye's second tenure as Chancellor, 1976-1982, is related to the Duke University Medical Center. Major subjects include Highland Hospital (Asheville, NC), the School of Nursing, and retrenchment. William G. Anlyan, Vice President for Health Affairs, is the primary correspondent within the series.
A subseries of the subject files created during Pye's second tenure as Chancellor, 1976-1982, contains files regarding various standing and ad hoc committees and files pertaining to planning committees and the University Long-Range Planning Committee. Other committees represented include the Athletic Council, Committee on the Social Implications of Duke's Investment Policies, search committees for a provost and a Vice-Chancellor for Data Processing, and the Undergraduate Faculty Council in the Arts and Sciences (UFCAS) Committee on Financial Aid and Admissions.
A subseries of the subject files created during Pye's second tenure as Chancellor, 1976-1982, consists of files created by staff assistants in the Chancellor's office, chiefly Gail Hagel and Jennifer Hillman. The files consist chiefly of information gathered in relation to long-range planning, including questionnaires, communications with members of the Long-Range Planning Committee, statistical data, and other materials.
The third series, A. Kenneth Pye Papers, 1968-1976, includes typescripts of speeches, correspondence, reports, and other material created during Pye's tenure as Dean of the School of Law, Chancellor, and University Counsel. The papers reflect matters outside of Duke University. The correspondence, spanning 1968 to 1974, includes letter from Pye's former law students and gives details about their careers and lives. Pye's responses are included. The correspondence further reflects Pye's work as an attorney and an educator, as it in part pertains to legal questions and issues. North Carolina Senator Sam Ervin and Chief Justice Warren Burger are among those who consulted with Pye on legal matters. The speeches and addresses, which are dated from 1968 to 1974, were primarily delivered at other institutions and relate to legal education and legal issues, including student demonstrations. Several subject files include reports and materials on university matters, including a public hearing on the ROTC, a 1975 report on teacher education at Duke, and reports from the Durham Urban Observatory, a joint research project between Duke, North Carolina Central University, and the city of Durham.
Related Material
H. Keith H. Brodie, Chancellor, Records, 1970 - 1985.
Duke University Archives
William G. Anlyan Papers, 1930-1995
Duke University Medical Center Archives
Office of the Chancellor Records
Duke University Archives
Barnes Woodhall, Chancellor, Records
Duke University Archives
Universities and colleges -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; Education, Higher -- North Carolina -- History; Duke University. Medical Center; Duke University. Chancellor; Duke University -- Planning; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University -- Administration; Brodie, H. Keith H. (Harlow Keith Hammond), 1939-; Anlyan, William G.; Sanford, Terry; Pye, A. Kenneth
- Chancellor of Duke University Records, 1970-1971
  - Subject Files, 1960-1971, bulk 1970-1971, undated
    Scope and Contents note
    This series consists of subject files created during Pye's first tenure as Chancellor, 1970-1971. Subjects include the merger of the Woman's College with Trinity College, an evaluation of the university's relationship with the Army Research Office in Durham, Duke's position on admission standards for student-athletes in the Atlantic Coast Conference, the Summer Transitional Program, international studies, the evaluation of the Navy and Air Force ROTC programs, African-American studies, the Pickets and Protest Policy and student unrest, and regulations pertaining to drug use and other aspects of student life. Administrative officers who communicated with Pye in regard to these matters include James Price, Dean of Undergraduate Education, William Griffith, Dean of Student Affairs, and President Terry Sanford.
    - Adams, J. L.: Management Services, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Adcock, Jack: Cost Accounting, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Administrative Committee on Development, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Administrative Committee on Long-Range Planning, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Administrative Council, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Admissions: Dr. Ballantyne, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action Plan, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action: Minority Groups, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action: Women, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Afro-American Society, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Alumni: Loyalty Fund, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Alumni: Miscellaneous (Meetings, Correspondence with, etc.), 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Alumni: Roger Marshall, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Angier B. Duke Scholarships: Program Study, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Archivist: Search Committee for University, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Army Research Office Durham, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - AROD: Summary of Activities and Expenditures of the Duke Coordination Office for fiscal year, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Atlantic Coast Conference, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Athletic Department: Miscellaneous, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Athletic Fund: Tom Butters, Executive Director, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Athletic Statement (Academic Standards), undated (Box 1)
    - Banks: Miscellaneous Matters, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Bond Management, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Bryson, E. C.: University Counsel, 1969-1971 (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Bubas, Vic: Director of Public Relations (Naming of Cameron Indoor Stadium), 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Budget, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Buildings, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Building Programming Committee: University Union, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Business Administration: School of, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Business Office: J. Peyton Fuller, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Business Office: Charles B. Huestis, 1969-1971 (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - C, General, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Chancellor's Advisory Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Chancellor's Office: A. K. Pye, 1970-1971 (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Chancellor/Provost Review Committee, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Commencement, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Community Health Sciences, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Computer and Data Processing, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
    - Cox, Richard L., Dean of Undergraduate Men (Letter of Appointment), 1969 (Box 2)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Closed until 2039.
    - Credit Union, 1971 (Box 2)
    - D, General, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
    - Duke Endowment, The, 1969-1971 (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Duke Family History, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Durham, City of (Duke-Durham Relationship), 1970 (Box 2)
    - Drug Policy, 1969-1971 (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Duke Broadcasting System (WDBS), undated (Box 2)
    - Engineering School, 1968-1971 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Handbook, and Newsletter (Handbook Revisions), 1969 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Salaries, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Status, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Federal Highways, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - Financial Aid, 1969-1971 (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Foundations: Miscellaneous, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - Fringe Benefits, 1966-1971 (Box 2)
      Closed until 2041.
    - Governance, University, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - Graduate School: John C. McKinney, 1969-1971 (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - Green, William (Duke in the News), 1971 (Box 2)
    - Griffith, W. J., 1969-1971 (Box 2)
    - Greenberg, Abe: Quail Ridge Project, 1969 (Box 2)
    - H, General, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
    - Harward, S. C., 1971 (Box 2)
    - Health Care, Committee on Legal Issues in, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Health Education and Welfare, Department of, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Health, National Institutes of, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Higher Education, North Carolina Board of, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - History, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Hobbs, Marcus E.: Provost, 1969-1970 (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Hospital Administration Program, Search Committee for Director of, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Hospital Care Commission, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Housing, Married Student, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - Inauguration: Mr. Sanford, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Inaugural: Committee, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Information Services (Clarence E. Whitefield), 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - Institutional Advancement: Frank Ashmore, Vice-President, 1969-1971 (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - Institutional Advancement: David Ross, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - Institutional Advancement: Craufurd Goodwin, 1969-1971 (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Institutional Advancement: F. Roger Thaler (Associate Director of Development), 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - Institutional Advancement: Paul A. Robell (Foundations Relations Officer), 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - Institutional Advancement: Dorothy Brock (Gift Records Office), 1970-1971 (Box 3)
    - Institutional Advancement: Gifts and Grants (Reports), 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Institutional Advancement: University Editor, 1969-1973 (Box 3)
    - Institutional Advancement: Campaign Report for 5th Decade Program, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - Institutional Advancement: Proposals, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Institutional Advancement: Foundation Handbook, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Institutional Advancement: Internal Dev. & Alumni Relations Council, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Intramural Building, 1971 (Box 3)
    - K, General, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - L, General, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Labor, U. S. Department of, (Minority Students), 1971 (Box 3)
    - Law Enforcement Assistance Administration: U. S. Department of Justice, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - Law School: Joseph T. Sneed, Dean, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
    - Law School, 1969-1970 (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Law School: Frank T. Read, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - Law School: F. Hodge O'Neal, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - Lee, Howard: Paths for Employee Progress, 1969-1971 (Box 4)
    - Library, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - Liquor, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - M, General, 1969-1971 (Box 4)
    - Mary Duke Biddle Foundation, 1966-1970 (Box 4)
    - Marine Laboratory, Duke University, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - Married Student Housing, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - Medical Center: W. G. Anlyan, 1970-1971 (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Medical Center: Board of Visitors, 1967-1971 (Box 4)
    - Medical Center: Dr. Harvey Estes (Department of Community Health Sciences), 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - Medical Center: Fiscal Feasibility Study Reports, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Medical Center: Miscellaneous, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - Medical Center: Dr. Stuart M. Sessoms, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Medical Center: Jeff Steinert, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - Medical Center: Eye Center, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Medical Center: Nursing School, 1969-1971 (Box 4)
    - N, General, 1969-1971 (Box 4)
    - NASA, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - National Merit Scholarship Corporation, 1969-1971 (Box 4)
    - Non-Academic Employees: Salaries, etc., 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - North Carolina Association of Independent Colleges and Universities, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - North Carolina Department of Air and Water Resources (Duke Forest), 1969 (Box 4)
    - NROTC Colleges, Association of, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - Operation Breakthrough, 1968-1970 (Box 4)
    - Organization Study, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Pan-Africa: USA International Track Meet, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Pennsylvania Higher Education Assistance Agency, 1970-1971 (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Pickets and Protest Policy, 1969-1970 (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Pickets and Protest Policy: Student Unrest, 1969-1970 (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Placement Office: Patricia O'Connor, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Policy Sciences: Joel Fleishman, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Political Activity: IRS, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Political Science, Department of, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Policies: Internal Revenue Service, 1970-1972 (Box 5)
    - President's Report, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
    - Presidential Search Committee, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Price, James L.: Vice-Provost and Dean of Undergraduate Education, 1969-1971 (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Priorities, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
    - Psychology, Department of (Psychical Research Foundation), 1970 (Box 5)
    - Publications, University, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
    - Publishers, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
    - Q: Miscellaneous and Questionnaires, 1969-1971
      - Includes responses to questionnaires sent to Duke University from other institutions regarding legal and paralegal education, institutions of higher learning, academic governance, and student unrest. (Box 5)
    - R, General, 1969-1971 (Box 5)
    - Regional Programs, 1969-1971 (Box 5)
    - Registrar, University, 1969-1971 (Box 5)
    - Retirement, 1963-1971 (Box 5)
    - Richardson, Elliott L.: HEW Secretary, 1971 (Box 5)
    - ROTC, 1969-1970 (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - RTI: Board of Governors, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
    - S to Z: File Guide, undated (Box 5)
    - S, General, 1969-1971 (Box 5)
    - Sabbaticals, 1969-1971 (Box 5)
    - Sanford, Terry (President), 1970-1971 (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Scott, Robert: Governor, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Sea Level Hospital, 1968-1969 (Box 5)
    - Sea Level Hospital: Advisory Board, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Security, 1968-1971 (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Segregated Durham Facilities, 1970 (Box 6)
    - Sidewalks: Duke Forest, 1970 (Box 6)
    - Southern Universities (Council of Southern Universities), 1971 (Box 6)
    - Slavic Languages and Literature, Department of (University Center for Rational Alternatives), 1969 (Box 6)
    - Southern Regional Education Board, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Spengler, Joseph, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
    - Sponsored Programs, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Statement of Intent Forms (Grants), 1970-1971 (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Student Health, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Student Political Involvement, 1970 (Box 6)
    - Student Publications, 1970 (Box 6)
    - Student Union, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Students: Associated Students of Duke University, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Students: Black, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Students: Foreign, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
    - Summer Session Reports, 1969-1970 (Box 6)
    - Superannuated Ministers, Duke Endowment Fund for, 1969-1970 (Box 6)
    - T, General, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Telephone Information, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
    - TIAA-CREF, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
    - TIAA-CREF Hearing, Raleigh, NC, 1971 June 29 (Box 6)
    - Traffic Commission: Parking, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Triangle Universities Consortium on Air Pollution, 1970 (Box 6)
    - Triangle Universities Computation Center, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Trinity College: Dean Hugh M. Hall, 1970 (Box 6)
    - Troika: Agenda, Miscellaneous, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - U, General, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Undergraduate Research Assistantship Program, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Union 1199, 1969-1970 (Box 6)
    - Union: Local Union 1199D, 1970 (Box 6)
    - United Durham, Inc., 1971 (Box 6)
    - United Fund, 1969-1972 (Box 6)
    - University Associates, 1970-1971 (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Universities National Anti-War Fund, 1970 (Box 6)
    - Urban Renewal, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
    - Urban Studies Committee, 1971 (Box 6)
    - W, General, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Ward, James (Architect), 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Warlick, Jennifer: Reports, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Washington Summer Intern Program, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
    - Woman's College: General, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Woman's College: Juanita Kreps, Dean, 1969-1970 (Box 6)
    - Wood, George: Editor, The Above Ground Review, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Yearbook, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
- Chancellor of Duke University Records, 1976-1982
  - Subject Files, 1969-1983, bulk 1976-1982
    This series consists of subject files created during Pye's second tenure as Chancellor, 1976-1982. As Chancellor, Pye had overall responsibility for planning and budgeting at the university, and the files reflect the retrenchment and long-range planning process that occurred at Duke in the late 1970s and early 1980s. Other subjects include reports on the enrollment of North Carolina students, the admission of African-Americans, A.B. Duke Scholars from the years 1926 to 1981, financial aid and admissions, the Duke University Athletic Association (DUAA), the recruitment and admission of student-athletes, the Commission on Intercollegiate Athletics of the American Council on Education, Title IX of the Education Amendments, affirmative action, planning for the University Center (Bryan University Center), East Campus planning and residential life, the Public Safety department, black affairs, labor relations and unionization, the Nixon Library controversy, the American Dance Festival, the Marine Laboratory, and forestry, nursing, sociology, and education programs.
    - A, 1976-1980 (Box 7)
    - Academic Council: Richard L. Watson, Chairman, 1976-1977 (Box 7)
    - Academic Council: Anne Scott, Chairman, 1977-1978 (Box 7)
    - Academic Council: Lawrence Evans, Chairman, 1979-1981 (Box 7)
    - Academic Council: Roy Weintraub, Chairman, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
    - Academic Integrity, 1979 (Box 7)
    - Accounting, 1978-1979 (Box 7)
    - Adcock, John F., Controller, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
    - Admissions, 1979-1980 (Box 7)
    - Admissions: Dr. Clark Cahow, 1976-1982 (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Admissions: Inquiries Concerning Applicants and Miscellaneous Materials, 1977-1982 (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Admissions: Jean Scott, Director, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
    - Admissions: Texas Project, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
    - Aerospace Studies (Charles W. Duncan), 1970-1978 (Box 7)
    - Aging and Human Development, Center for the Study of, 1976-1982 (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Alumni: Meetings and Correspondence, 1976-1980 (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Alumni: Office of the Director, 1976-1980 (Box 7)